<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects on Tong Shen</title>
    <link>/project/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Projects on Tong Shen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 27 Nov 2017 00:00:00 -0600</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title> Fine-Grained Visual Categorization on iNaturalist dataset</title>
      <link>/project/fine-grained-visual-categorization-inaturalist/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Nov 2017 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/fine-grained-visual-categorization-inaturalist/</guid>
      <description>Table of Content  Overview Main Difficulties  Data Imbalance Weakly supervised label Data insufficiency  Fine-tuned model on ImageNet pretrained model. Fine-grained Classification  Super-category classification Fine-grained classification in single super-category  Bilinear model Attention model(Class Activation Map)   Reference materials  Overview I run into this challenge at early April. This dataset contains about 0.4 million images spanning over 8142 categories. Without expert knowledge, many of these species are extremely difficult to accurately classify due to their visual similarity.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Obfuscated/Blurred Human Face Reconstruction</title>
      <link>/project/obfuscatedblurred-human-face-reconstruction/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Nov 2017 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/obfuscatedblurred-human-face-reconstruction/</guid>
      <description>Table of Contents  Data preparation Super Resolution ResNet Generative Adversarial Network Model  Nowadays, a lot of images on the Internet are intentionally blurred or mosaiced due to various reasons. The main objective of this project is to reconstruct these images, especially heavily blurred ones, to their original high-resolution counterpart. This problem is an ill-posed problems, we need to predict fine-grained details only based on little information on degenerated images.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>